A Guide to the Papers of Senator Harry F. Byrd, Jr.,
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Senator Harry F. Byrd, Jr.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10320-k
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Access to the Harry F. Byrd, Jr., Papers is controlled by the Honorable Harry F. Byrd, Jr. An applicant for access who is not associated with the University of Virginia must furnish to the Director of Special Collections a brief description of his academic or other qualifications, a summary of his research project, and a description of any projected publication that might make use of material from, or material derived from, the Harry F. Byrd, Jr., Papers. The Director of Special Collections will contact Senator Byrd and will notify the applicant of the Senator's decision.
Acquisition Information
These papers were given to the University of Virginia Library by Harry F. Byrd, Jr., Winchester, Virginia, on May 26, 2005.
Biographical/Historical Information
Harry Flood Byrd, Jr., a former member of the Virginia Senate (1947-1965), United States Senator for Virginia (1965-1983), and newspaper executive, was born in Winchester, Virginia, on December 20, 1914, son of Harry F. Byrd, Sr. and Anne Douglas (Beverley) Byrd. He was a student at the Virginia Military Institute, 1931-1933, and the University of Virginia, 1933-1935. Byrd married Gretchen B. Thomson of New Orleans, on August 9, 1941, and they had three children, Harry, Thomas Thomson, and Beverley.
Appointed to the United States Senate in 1965, Senator Byrd was elected to the Senate in 1966 as a Democrat and was reelected in 1970 and 1976 as an Independent. He was the first person in the history of the Senate to be elected twice as an Independent. Byrd was active on both the Armed Services Committee and the Finance Committee. He was also a member of the Virginia Democratic Central Committee (1940-1966).
Byrd was the editor of the Winchester Evening Star from 1935-, publisher of the Harrisonburg, Virginia, Daily News Record, 1937-; President and Director of the Rockingham Publishing Company, from 1946; director of the Associated Press, 1950-1966.
During World War II, he served as an executive officer of a patrol bombing squadron in the Central and Western Pacific as a Lieutenant Commander in the United States Naval Reserve. Byrd was a recipient of the Honor Medal, and a member of the Veterans of Foreign Wars, the American Legion, Rotarian Club, National Press Club, and the Army-Navy Club.
Scope and Content
This addition to the papers of Senator Harry F. Byrd, Jr. consists of 370 items (2 Hollinger boxes, ca. 1 linear foot), ca. 1960, 1966, 1982-2005. The papers contain manuscripts (electrostatic copies), typescripts and page proofs for Defying the Odds: An Independent Senator's Historic Campaign by Harry F. Byrd, Jr.; correspondence concerning the publication of Defying the Odds and responses from recipients and other readers to the book, many of whom wrote about their own involvement in or reminiscences about the 1970 campaign. Many of the responses were from U.S. Senators, members of the Virginia legislature, members of the media, and close friends of Byrd.
Also present are news clippings concerning Defying the Odds, the burial of Harry F. Byrd, Sr. and miscellaneous honors awarded to Harry F. Byrd, Jr., including the New Market Medal awarded to Harry F. Byrd, Jr. by VMI (2005 May 16); awards and honors, including resolutions and statues; and photographs. The collection also contains a letter from Richard E. Byrd to Dear Rixey [Smith], January 29, 1948.
Contents List
- Award - National Associated Businessmen Watchdog of the Treasury Award, 1971-1972, Oversize. (Box 1)
- Award- Man-Boy Americanism Award to Senator Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1973, Oversize (Box 1)
  In Recognition of Distinguished and Unselfish Service to our Nation, State and Northern Virginia Communities.
- Award- 94th Congress National Federation of Independent Business Guardian of Small Business Award, ca. 1975, Oversize. (Box 1)
- Award- Boy Scouts of America Great Salt Lake Council Appreciation Award, 1981 February 27, Oversize. (Box 1)
- Correspondence concerning the publication of Defying the Odds: An Independent Senator's Historic Campaign,1998 April-July (Box 1)
  Correspondents include several persons who sent editing suggestions: J. Edward Grimsley, Charles L. Bartlett, Nelson Hyde, and James J. Kilpatrick; Larry J. Sabato, who wrote the preface; and several persons who wrote blurb statements for the book: Senator Sam Nunn (fax), Senator Russell B. Long (fax), and Charles McDowell.
- Correspondence concerning the publication of Defying the Odds: An Independent Senator's Historic Campaign,1998 August-October (Box 1)
- Correspondence concerning responses to Defying the Odds: An Independent Senator's Historic Campaign,1998 October-November (Box 1)
  Correspondents include: George F. Allen, Lewis Allen, Hunter B. Andrews, William L. Armstrong, John Ashcroft, Charles L. Bartlett, Frank Batten, Fitzgerald Bemiss, David S. Broder, David Tennant Bryan, J. Stewart Bryan III, Judge James L. Buckley, Robert C. Byrd, George M. Cochran, Thad Cochran, John Warren Cooke, Paul D. Coverdell, Pete V. Domenici, Thomas N. Downing, Mark L. Earley, Gerald Ford, James S. Gilmore, III, Mills E. Godwin, Jr. (2 letters), Virgil H. Goode, Bob Goodlatte, Alan Greenspan, Ed Grimsley, Orrin G. Hatch, Jesse Helms, Nelson Hyde, J.J. Jewett, Paul Laxalt, Joseph I. Lieberman, Bob Livingston, Russell B. Long, Richard G. Lugar, Connie Mack, Mike Mansfield, John F. McNair, III, Patrick Munroe, W. Tayloe Murphy, Jr., Don Nickles, Herman J. Obermayer, Cokie Roberts, Sandra Mims Rowe, George Warren Shanks, Richard T. Short, Arlen Specter, William C. Stuart III, Fred Thompson, and Strom Thurmond.
- Correspondence concerning responses to Defying the Odds: An Independent Senator's Historic Campaign,1998 December-1999 January (Box 1)
  Correspondents include: Robert F. Bennett, Lloyd Bentsen, George Bush, Robert C. Fitzgerald, Judge Robert E. Gibson, Judge William H. Hodges, Ernest F. Hollings, Walter Dee Huddleston, Daniel K. Inouye, Patrick J. Leahy, Henry Luce III, Paul Saunier, Jr. (relates two anecdotes about Bill Tuck), Paul Simon, Howard K. Smith, Ted Stevens, Paul A. Volcker, Frank R. Wolf, and T. Eugene Worrell.
- Correspondence concerning responses to Defying the Odds: An Independent Senator's Historic Campaign,1999 February-2003 (Box 1)
  Correspondents include: Maryon Allen (anecdote about George Wallace), William Cohen, Mark O. Hatfield, Fred G. Pollard, William Rehnquist, Harrison H. Schmitt, John B. Updike (former staffer), Jesse Ventura, and Malcolm Wallop.
- Correspondence concerning responses to Defying the Odds: An Independent Senator's Historic Campaign,ca. 1998-2000, Correspondents include: Leslie D. Campbell, Jr., John T. Casteen, III, Clifford P. Hansen, Bill Mims, and Charles Wampler, Jr. (2 letters). (Box 1)
- Defying the Odds: An Independent Senator's Historic Campaign- Manuscript Chapters 1, 3, 6, 1998 April, Copies. (Box 1)
- Defying the Odds: An Independent Senator's Historic Campaign, 1998 May 31, Typescript Revision, 84 pages (Copy). (Box 1)
- Defying the Odds: An Independent Senator's Historic Campaign, 1998 July 21, Page Proofs and Dust Jacket Designs. (Box 1)
- News clippings concerning Senator Harry F. Byrd, Jr. and his book, Defying the Odds: An Independent Senator's Historic Campaign, the burial of his father, Harry F. Byrd, Sr. and miscellaneous honors awarded to Byrd, 1966, 1998-2005 (Box 2)
- Photographs of President Dwight Eisenhower and Senator Harry F. Byrd, Sr. (1960 Oct 27), including a letter of explanation dated October 21, 2003; and photograph of Virginia Senator Harry F. Byrd, Jr. giving a speech on the floor of the Virginia Senate (n.d.), 1960, n.d. (Box 2)
- Photographs of Cadets at Shenandoah Valley Military Academy, Winchester, Virginia, 1920's, Oversize. (Box 2)
- Photograph of the Associated Press Board of Directors, 1952, Oversize. (Box 2)
- Photograph of a Time Magazine quote concerning the 1970 Virginia Senate election and an actual newspaper heading from the Winchester Evening Star about the Byrd victory, 1970, Oversize. (Box 2)
- Proofs and Correspondence for a series of articles by Douglas B. O' Connell and Adrian O'Connor concerning the history of The Winchester Star which was later made into a book, 1996-1997 (Box 2)
- Resolutions concerning Harry F. Byrd, Jr. and the Winchester Star Leadership Awards and other Honors, 1982-2004 (Box 2)
- Senate Joint Resolution 179 honoring Senator Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 2002, Oversize. (Box 2)